<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joseph's entertainment of his bretheren in a sermon preached at the Herefordshire feast at St Mary-le-Bow, June the 25th. 1684 / by William Bolton.</title>
            <author>Bolton, William, 1650 or 51-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4320</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11792032</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11792032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 809:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Joseph's entertainment of his bretheren in a sermon preached at the Herefordshire feast at St Mary-le-Bow, June the 25th. 1684 / by William Bolton.</title>
                  <author>Bolton, William, 1650 or 51-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Miles Flesher, for Charles Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joseph --  (Son of Jacob)</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XLIII, 34 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Joſeph<hi>'s Entertainment of his Brethren:</hi> IN A SERMON Preached at the <hi>Herefordſhire Feaſt</hi> AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARY-LE-BOW, <hi>June</hi> the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM BOLTON,</hi> One of the School-Maſters of the <hi>Charter-Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Miles Fleſher,</hi> for <hi>Charles Harper,</hi> at the <hi>Flower-de-Luce</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:49251:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49251:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 43. Verſ. 34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And he took, and ſent Meſſes unto them, from before him (but <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s Meſs was five times ſo much, as any of theirs,) and they drank, and were merry with him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHEN I look into the Sacred Writings, I cannot ſufficiently admire at the Power, as well as Goodneſs of the Lord, in defeating Satan, by thoſe very means, whereby the old Serpent brought ruin to our firſt Parents: Man may now eat and live; and the Devil may ceaſe to boaſt of his conqueſt over Mankind in Paradiſe, when he tempted to eat of the forbidden tree: For if Man do not contribute to his own deſtruction, and miſuſe thoſe Creatures which God hath afforded for his benefit, for the entercourſe of Love and Friendſhip, as well as ſtay and ſupport of his life, he may go into a better Paradiſe, than that from which our firſt Parents were driven. Here's no Angel now with a flaming Sword, to bar us from entring thoſe more ſacred Manſions, and eating and drinking are become the Symbols,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49251:3"/>not onely of Chriſt's love to us, as in the holy Euchariſt, but of our love and kindneſs one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. Take a ſurvey of God's Church in all ages, and you will find the men thereof, (whether after any great mercy received, or a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of entring into a more familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) ſtill entertaining one another with theſe tokens of amity, <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> together. The <hi>Jews</hi> of old had a feaſt at the end of their Sacrifices; and the Primitive Chriſtians, if not in the very Apoſtles times, I am ſure immediately afterwards, their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Love-feaſts,</hi> after the Lord's Supper: That feaſting, or publick eating and drinking together, were the tyes of Union and Confederacy amongſt men, Satan knew well enough, therefore he encouraged this Cuſtome alſo amongſt his Proſelytes and Followers. Would <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> ſlay his brother <hi>Amnon?</hi> A feaſt is made the ſnare to entrap him. But that I may bring this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what home to our ownſelves; have ſeveral degrees and orders of men, whether in relation to their being born in the ſame Countrey, or otherwiſe, met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, firſt to celebrate God's praiſes in his own Houſe, and afterwards adjourning to ſome Common Hall, there engaged one another, in their duty towards their Prince, their adherence to the Succeſſion of the Crown in the right line, their Reciprocal love one with another, and the relieving the poor and neceſſitous? Have good and loyal men, as now, met together for this end and purpoſe? And have not the <hi>Catilines</hi> of our age, had their Cabals, and Aſſociations too, for the ruine of their, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid, too Gracious King, and his Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49251:3"/>for the Subverſion of the Laws, and their Countrey, and afterwards of themſelves too, as their Forefathers in the laſt Rebellion found it? <hi>What elſe meant their Kings-head, or Green-Ribbon Clubs, where many affronts to Sacred Majeſty were firſt hammered, before they received their Poliſhing by Votes in another place? But</hi> Abſalom <hi>hath a vow to be performed in</hi> Hebron: <hi>Tickets are therefore ſent abroad by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderminers of our</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which, forſooth, muſt be uſhered in, with the Pageantry of a Sermon too; but this their ſolemn Appearance was baffled and diſappointed by Authority; an happy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, without doubt, of our deliverance from the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it, I mean, the late Damnable and Fanatick Plot.</hi> I mention theſe and the like, to acquaint you, that it was the cuſtome of all Ages, for men, whether for good or bad deſigns, to ſtrengthen one another, by <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> together; and therefore long before the Law was given, you find <hi>Joſeph</hi> entertaining his brethren after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; witneſs the words of my Text; <hi>And he took, and ſent Meſſes unto them, from before him, and they drank, and were merry with him.</hi> The words do acquaint us, how <hi>Joſeph,</hi> one of the twelve ſons of Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> conſtituted by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Lord of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and inferiour to the King thereof, onely in Name and Title, entertained his eleven brethren, which twelve gave denomination after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the twelve Tribes or Counties of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> So that you ſee, my Text, and this ſolemn Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſo many of the ſame Countrey, do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and carry a Reſemblance one with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49251:4"/>
            <p>In handling of which words, I ſhall doe theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew you, what that place and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was, which <hi>Joſeph</hi> enjoyed, at this entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his brethren: <hi>And he,</hi> that is, the Lord of the Countrey; for <hi>Joſeph</hi> had not as yet diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himſelf to his brethren.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Reaſon why.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The manner how he entertained his brethren; <hi>And he took, and ſent Meſſes unto them, from before him, and they drank, and were merry with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall endeavour to vindicate ſuch Meetings as this.</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, by way of Application, from the Conſideration of the perſon <hi>entertaining,</hi> and the parties <hi>entertained.</hi> I ſhall propoſe ſome Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Inferences, fitting for ſuch Aſſemblies.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. Firſt therefore, as to the Place and Dignity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I might here give you an Hiſtorical account of <hi>Joſeph</hi> before his promotion; as what he ſuffered in <hi>Canaan</hi> from his unnatural brethren, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what befell him in <hi>Egypt,</hi> from the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of his age, when he was ſold, to his thirtieth, when he was advanced by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the King thereof; but I conſider, 'tis but your turning at your leiſure to the laſt part of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and you have a plain, as full, relation of him.</p>
               <p>As to the Place and Dignity, which he held at this entertainment; it was as great as a Sovereign Prince was able to confer upon him, or a Subject capable
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49251:4"/>of receiving: <hi>Foraſmuch,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> chap. 41. verſ. 30. and ſo on, <hi>as God hath ſhewed thee all this, there is none ſo diſcreet, and wiſe as thou art; thou ſhalt be over my houſe, and according unto thy word ſhall all my people be ruled; onely in the Throne will I be greater than thou.</hi> A Commiſſion you ſee very large, and therefore though the occaſion and the circumſtance of the time of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement might ſeem to countenance, yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubſcribe to their conjectures, who would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Joſeph</hi> no other than a <hi>Praefectus Annonae,</hi> who was to take care of the Corn, that the people of the land might not ſuffer famine; Although I ſhall grant, that this place of Truſt, was very honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not onely in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but other Nations; ſo honourable amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, after he had ſubdued <hi>Mithridates,</hi> the moſt powerfull Prince of <hi>Aſia;</hi> nay after he had tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed, over a great part of the World, thought it an honour to have this of <hi>Praefectus Annonae</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his other Titles: Though this Dignity, I ſay, was very great, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> particularly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted this Office alſo; yet his authority was grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: He managed all affairs of State; he had the power of Life and Death, of making War, and Peace; in a word, he had the whole ſway of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment devolved upon him: The authority of ſuch Regents (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was conſtituted in this Chapter) was of that figure and eſtimation in the world, both then, and afterwards, that they were many times miſtaken for the Kings themſelves, by people of other Nations. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s brethren, I am ſure, took him for ſuch, witneſs thoſe words
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49251:5"/>of theirs to their Father, chap. 42. verſ. 30. <hi>The man who is the Lord of the Land;</hi> and again, <hi>the Lord of the Countrey:</hi> Nay the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers inſerted ſeveral of theſe Regents amongſt the Kings themſelves, otherwiſe their Catalogue muſt be very imperfect, and never to be reconciled; And ſuch was the <hi>Soldans</hi> power afterwards in <hi>Egypt,</hi> under the <hi>Caliphs;</hi> ſuch the Maſters of the Palace, under the old Kings of <hi>France;</hi> and ſuch the Grand <hi>Viziers,</hi> perhaps at this time in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: Such, ſo great in Authority, as well as Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Wiſedom, as the Scripture informs us, was the perſon, who <hi>took and ſent Meſſes unto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Which brings me to my ſecond Particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. The Reaſon why <hi>Joſeph</hi> entertained them at a Feaſt or Banquet.</head>
               <p>Ten of his brethren had been with him before, to buy Corn; to whom he then ſeemed rough and ſevere, either to make them repent of their former uſage towards him, or fearing, that they might have been, as cruel to <hi>Benjamin,</hi> his onely Brother by the ſame Mother, as before to him; he charged them therefore as Spies, ſecured one of them in bonds, till the reſt brought <hi>Benjamin</hi> with them into <hi>Egypt:</hi> Let but him once appear, the ſcene is altered; and all the Clouds of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s ſeeming indignation are gone and vaniſhed, and they might even then, before he diſcovered himſelf unto them, have read the kindneſs of a brother; As ſoon as they come to Court, <hi>Joſeph</hi> immediately commands, <hi>Kill and ſlay, for theſe men ſhall dine with me.</hi> And now <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s brethren may lay aſide all fear; this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49251:5"/>banquet, to which they are invited, gives them more than hopes, both of their own ſafety, and the Prince's favour: <hi>Simeon</hi> is releaſed, and all of them from ſuſpected ſpies find themſelves gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with dining with <hi>the Lord of the Countrey:</hi> A Banquet is thought by <hi>Joſeph</hi> to be the beſt way of receiving them, both as their Brother, and their Lord: They had enough paid that adoration, and obedience to him, of which he had formerly dreamed, and which had cauſed their malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; he had with joy often underſtood their Repentance, as to what they had formerly done to him; he views his brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> grown to mans eſtate, whom he had left in <hi>Canaan</hi> a little child; and can ſcarcely forbear embracing him, and diſcovering by his tenderneſs, who he was; he is ſatisfied that his Father is well; he can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now no longer treat them, as theirs and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Lord, but thinks it high time to conſult his brotherly affections too: Which to effect, he orders, that they ſhould dine with him; and this was the moſt ready and natural means, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> could make uſe of, or indeed his brethren expect; had they then known, how nearly he was related to them: And therefore, in the book of <hi>Eſther, Haman,</hi> in my opinion, urged very well; (though the Event, through his demerits, proved other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,) that <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his King did deſign him favour, when he admitted him of all his Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers to dine with him. Eating and drinking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ever was a token of friendſhip amongſt all people: Inſomuch, that I read of the <hi>Romans</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, that they had their Annual <hi>Chariſtia,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49251:6"/>like to our Countrey feaſts at this time, when kinfolk and relations met together, to confirm, ſaith my Authour, their friendſhip one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reconcile all different parties, who had lived in any variance before. Fanſie therefore, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, the twelve brethren ſate down at dinner; <hi>Joſeph</hi> indeed, as a Prince, ſerved at a Table by himſelf; as it is before my Text; but as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too, he admits them to dine in the ſame room near unto him: which leads me to my other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III. The manner how he entertained them;</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he took and ſent Meſſes unto them, from before him; and they drank, and were merry with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not, as ſome have done upon the words, lay down any Critical queſtions; as whether it was alway a cuſtome for Princes to ſit alone at Table by themſelves, by way of State and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur; or whether ſitting, as here in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along, as amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> from them in our Saviour's time, bore the moſt ancient date; or whether it hath been a practice for Princes to ſend diſhes from their own Table to their Favourites, as is reported of <hi>Cyrus</hi> amongſt the <hi>Perſians, Ageſilaus</hi> amongſt the <hi>Grecians,</hi> and ſeveral of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours? or why the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> as in the Context, ſate at one Table by themſelves, and the <hi>Hebrews</hi> at another by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; Neither farther ſhall I enquire, what the Meſſes were, which <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent to his brethren, taking it for granted, that they were rich and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49251:6"/>ſumptuous, ſuch as might ſet forth his magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as well as kindneſs; neither, laſtly, ſhall I ask, why <hi>Benjamin</hi> had <hi>five times ſo much as the reſt,</hi> as you read in my Text, points indeed incident enough to my Theme, but wholly averſe to my deſign, which is not to nauſeate you with intricate queſtions, a trouble both to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators themſelves, and their Readers too.</p>
               <p>But I muſt not omit the giving you the genuine ſignification of the laſt words of the Text, <hi>viz. They drank, and were merry.</hi> At the firſt view thereof, the Debauchees of our, as well as of Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s age, might hug themſelves, with having <hi>Joſeph</hi> a Pious and Wiſe man, yet a Patron of their exceſs and drunkenneſs: Let therefore the ſame Father's anſwer ſerve the men of our, as well as his time. The word in the Hebrew, ſaith he, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to drink <hi>plentifully,</hi> or <hi>cheerfully,</hi> by way of refreſhment onely; and it is applied even to ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate Creatures: Thus <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65. v. 9. <hi>Inebriaſti terram,</hi> thou haſt <hi>refreſhed,</hi> or <hi>watered</hi> the Earth; which being there acknowledged, as a gift of God, cannot be taken in a bad ſenſe. If this will not ſatisfie, let them reade the 2d Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> where they will find the ſame word with the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint in my Text; and upon the Occaſion of a Feaſt too; which Feaſt the bleſſed Jeſus did not onely grace with his own preſence, but honoured it alſo with the firſt miracle he wrought; and as after his Reſurrection he made himſelf known to his Diſciples by breaking of bread; ſo here at the Marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> he manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49251:7"/>by turning water into wine; as if thereby he deſigned, not onely to ſupply their preſent neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but remove ſuch ſcruples, as men of more nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than piety might afterwards raiſe: which brings me to my fourth and laſt Particular, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV. To endeavour to vindicate ſuch Meetings as this of ours.</head>
               <p>And of this too, I ſhall be ſhort, as having hinted at it in the Preface to my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; neither do I think it fitting to trouble ſuch Meetings as this with any long diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>And this I ſhall doe from the practice of the Patriarchs before the Law, of the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law; I might add of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the Law of nature, and finally of the Primitive Chriſtians (a body made up of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi>) under the Goſpel. Let three Angels viſit <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull; he orders a Calf to be dreſt to entertain them; and ſo far were they from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offended at his courteous invitation, though they had no need of it, that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.5. they commanded him to <hi>doe as he had ſaid;</hi> and my Text acquaints us, how <hi>Joſeph</hi> entertained his brethren.</p>
               <p>Under the Law, I might give you many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; I ſhall name but one; yet ſuch an one, as was annually kept for many ſucceeding years; from <hi>Judas Macchabaeus,</hi> till our bleſſed Saviour's time; and then it was ſo far from being diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanc'd by our Lord, that he himſelf juſtified the obſervation of it, by his own preſence. <hi>Joſephus</hi> acquaints us very ſuccinctly, with the reaſon of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49251:7"/>that Feaſt: When <hi>Judas Macchabaeus</hi> had re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the Service of the Temple, which had been for a long time polluted by the Heathens, both he and his Countrey-men ſolemnized a Feaſt: And this, without doubt, gave occaſion to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians, of inſtituting their <hi>Encoenia,</hi> or annual Feaſts at the Conſecration of their Churches, the ſame with our Countrey Wakes, ſo generally obſerved, I am ſure in thoſe places where I lived in <hi>Herefordſhire;</hi> though perhaps the Reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of not ſo well known.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour's Parable of the Prodigal Son is much to the ſame purpoſe: Let the Penitent Son return to his home, as well as his duty; the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and compaſſionate Father commands the beſt fatted Calf to be ſlain, to bid him welcome; And the preſence of the bleſſed Jeſus, at the two Feaſts before mentioned, ſufficiently declare his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of ſuch Meetings. I ſhall not inſiſt upon the Practice of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as knowing that of old, the <hi>Hereticks called</hi> Cathari, <hi>and the Puritans now, agreeable both in name and nature,</hi> did and do as falſly, as maliciouſly, decry ſuch Feaſts, as taking their riſe from the cuſtome of the Heathens.</p>
               <p>Proceed we therefore to the times of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. If we reade ſo ſeldom of Feaſts amongſt the ancient Fathers, 'tis becauſe of the Perſecution of God's Church in thoſe Elder days; yet even then we ſhall not want ſufficient Teſtimonies: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was a Canon of St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention of in his Epiſtles, and who was the firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop of both the <hi>Gentile</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Churches; and who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49251:8"/>within one remove, ſucceeded the bleſſed Apoſtles, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> not onely in the then pure and untainted See of <hi>Rome,</hi> but in their Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> is copious, how he and other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans kept ſuch Feaſts; And at the <hi>Dypticks,</hi> or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of famous men, who ſealed their faith in Chriſt with their bloud; the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did indulge themſelves, and take a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt than at other times. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in ſeveral places gives us his concurrence with us: We keep Feſtival-days, ſaith he in one place; and in his Oration <hi>in Sanctum Baptiſma,</hi> at the beginning thereof, he ſeems to conteſt for ſuch Meetings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Hereticks of his time: It is fitting, ſaith he, that men ſhould annually celebrate, and rejoice in ſuch, and ſuch days; and then names the days; either wherein they were born, or baptized, or married, <hi>vel locum aliquem primi incoluerunt,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to our Countrey feaſt at this time; and then, as if he deſpiſed the unreaſonable Cavils of the Hereticks, by an alluſion to the Pagan Rites and Ceremonies, he declares how Pious and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtians did ſolemnize their Feaſts. After this manner, from that Father, the ſtout and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prelate <hi>Mountague</hi> informs me, <hi>That</hi> Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, <hi>who aſſerted the cauſe of our Eſtabliſh't Church, not onely againſt</hi> Baronius, <hi>that Bulwark of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Chair, but the</hi> Puritans <hi>likewiſe, and thoſe alſo backed by an Houſe of Commons too; yet did not that daunt him from taking off the Fig-leaves that Party had put on, to hide, if it were poſſible, their errors and enmity to our Church.</hi> I muſt confeſs, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49251:8"/>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> often blamed the Chriſtians for their riot and exceſs at ſuch Meetings; and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chid them for immoderately drinking the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's health; And though the drinking of the Prince's health, was decreed by the Senate, to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar,</hi> and never, as I have read, cancell'd by any Edict of Chriſtian Emperours; yet <hi>Peter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> in his Appendix, cites St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Cuſtome of his time: <hi>Bibamus, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, pro ſalute Imperatoris,</hi> &amp;c. Let us drink, ſay they, the Emperour's health, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to any unbiaſs'd Reader, doth not ſo much find fault with the thing it ſelf, as with the ill manner of doing it: And the general practice of the Loyal, and conſequently the beſt part of our Nation, doth explain HIs preſent Majeſty's Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as to the drinking of his Health, <hi>viz.</hi> that it doth not ſo much forbid the thing, as the exceſs therein; and that we ſhould not impair our own health, whilſt we wiſh his. And this ſhall ſerve for the Explication of my Text; I ſhall now beg your patience for the Applicatory part, and I have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <p>Firſt therefore, from <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s thus courteouſly entertaining his ten brothers, who before had been ſo cruel, barbarous and unnatural to him, as the Scriptures will fully inform you: Let me recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that grand duty of Chriſtianity, of pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Enemies, and forgiving thoſe, whom you may fanſie, have done you any injury. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you to which duty, I ſhall intreat your leave to propoſe a new and living example to you;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49251:9"/>but ſuch an one, as is not impertinent either to my Text, or this Loyal Aſſembly; the Motto of whoſe chief Town, <hi>Invictae fidelitatis praemium,</hi> proclaims their conſtant fidelity to their Prince, even in the worſt of times; much more now, when Schiſm and Faction, when Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion are wiſely, as juſtly, diſcountenanc'd and puniſhed, and all men are, or pretend to be ſo, Loyaliſts: You may eaſily judge whom I mean, without my naming our preſent Sovereign, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween whom and <hi>Joſeph</hi> there ſeems a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance. Compare their Age, you will find them both commencing at the ſame time in their Miſeries, and in their Glory: <hi>Both of them about the ſame years were forced from their Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; the one by unnatural brethren, the other by more inhumane Subjects.</hi> But our King's Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were greater than <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s; He was but the eleventh Son, and ſo could not expect any great inheritance, whilſt our King was the eldeſt, and heir to three flouriſhing Kingdoms. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he was ſold, had the comfort not to fear any hurt to be offered to <hi>Jacob;</hi> whilſt our diſconſolate So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign laments his Father, as murthered by the worſt of Villains, and that under a Mock-ſhew of Juſtice: <hi>Joſeph</hi> had but one brother <hi>Benjamin</hi> to be concerned for, our Prince had two, the one indeed a Companion of his Exile and miſeries, but young <hi>Gloceſter</hi> expoſed to the barbarity of Hypocritical Rakehells, whoſe very Mercy did threaten more, than others Cruelty; for if they ſhould for their own ends, as the old King feared, have forced the Crown upon his Head, he knew 'twould be like
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49251:9"/>the Royal ſlaves, amongſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> to ſacrifice him afterwards: Beſides, our King had many Loyal Subjects, continually haraſs'd with Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Sequeſtrations, and ſuch-like tenderneſſes of the pretended Saints, nay even with Death it ſelf, which could not but grieve his Princely heart. Farther, there was this difference between the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the one, and the Rebels againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>The one ſold</hi> Joſeph, <hi>that they might not be branded as Murtherers of their brother; The other proffer'd one thouſand pound for his Perſon, that they might, without doubt, doubly dye their accurſed hands with the bloud of the Son, as well as the Father.</hi> And thus much as to their Sufferings. Now let us view them in their glory and power, and ſee how the one treated his offending, but penitent, brethren; the other, <hi>His then, I wiſh to God, they may not ſtill prove his Rebellious Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; And the laſt Plot doth more than juſtifie ſuch fears.</hi> But let us view them in their Glory. The Scripture acquaints us, that <hi>Joſeph, when he was thirty years old, ſtood before</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and received that Royal Commiſſion of governing the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt; and none of you are ignorant, at what age God bleſs'd theſe Kingdoms, with the happy return of our preſent Sovereign.</hi> Both of them came to their power; the one to a deputed, the other to his own by inheritance, by the very ſame means: <hi>It was God, and God alone, who raiſed</hi> Joſeph; <hi>and the ſame God, who reſtored</hi> Charles <hi>the Second; without making uſe of the boaſted inſtruments, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Canaanitiſh Brethren, or Engliſh Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians:</hi> Joſeph <hi>therefore, as ſoon as he had made
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49251:10"/>himſelf known to his brethren,</hi> chap. 45. verſ. 8. <hi>for fear that they ſhould plead, that their ſelling him, brought him into Egypt, and conſequently to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion therein, tells them plainly to their faces,</hi> It was not ye that ſent me hither, but God; and he hath made me a Father to <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and a Ruler throughout all the land of Egypt. <hi>And in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> Redeunte Carolo, <hi>was not onely an ingenious and witty, but a pious and ſolid argument, that one made uſe of, to prove the exiſtence of God; for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than an Almighty Arm could have ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppoſe them both in their full luſtre and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; though we know who they were (thoſe great Pretenders, and but Pretenders to the King's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration) who would have limited our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regn's juſt Power; and like <hi>Philip,</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> would have our King govern, as the other complained, that he was ſent to conquer Kingdoms with fetters and ſhackles on him.</p>
               <p>Behold them both, I ſay, with their Sceptres in their hands, the one governing <hi>Egypt</hi> under <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> the other of his own right giving Laws to his <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and other Subjects. The Scripture tells us, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> after two years, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment of one of his Perſecutours, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give them any other name, till his Clemency reſtored them to that affectionate title, which by their cruelty they had forfeited; I ſay, after he had impriſoned one of them for a long ſpace, after he had often known their ſorrow, as to what they had formerly done to him; inſtead of puniſhing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49251:10"/>thoſe who had been ſo unnatural and barbarous to him; he kindly invites them to dine with him, and as in my Text, courteouſly entertains them, and which too, was onely an earneſt of his future favours, for ſoon after with tears of joy he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himſelf unto them, and laying aſide the Robes of Majeſty, embraced them with the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of a brother; and gave them the richeſt part of <hi>Egypt,</hi> even the land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> to inhabit and dwell therein: But ſtill they were his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nay his elder brothers too, whom <hi>Joſeph</hi> thus forgave and obliged. And did our King treat his Rebellious Subjects with leſs pity and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Some few excepted of thoſe impious Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, who had the Impudence to ſit in pretended Juſtice upon, and ſentence to death the Sacred Perſon of his Royal Father: Thoſe few excepted, I ſay, for example ſake, whom neither his own Piety, nor the cries of his Martyred Father's bloud, nor the juſt Reſentments of his then Loyal Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would ſuffer to live any longer: With what mercy did he receive all the reſt? So far was he from puniſhing, that he ſeemed more concerned for them, than they for themſelves. <hi>How impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient was he, till all his Rebellious Subjects might know themſelves ſafe and ſecure; witneſs his haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and urging forwards his Gracious Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity? Wherein he excluded no curſing</hi> Shimei's, <hi>or other Traitours of a larger ſize, but gave a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral pardon to all; as if, like</hi> David, <hi>after the quelling of</hi> Abſalon<hi>'s Rebellion,</hi> 2 Sam. 19.22. <hi>he likewiſe were reſolved to ſay to any repining ſons of</hi> Zeruiah, Shall there any man be put to death?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49251:11"/>
                  <hi>Know I not, that I am this day King over Great</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>and</hi> Ireland? <hi>And if his Juſtice hath, as of late, ſeized upon ſome incorrigible Traitours: Is it not, becauſe all kinder methods of his mercy were loſt upon them, and they became doubly guilty of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, as well as Treaſon? But ſome may ſay, that</hi> Joſeph <hi>never puniſhed his offending brethren afterwards, I ſhall eaſily grant it; but then it is as true, that his brethren were ſo far from reiterating their iniquities, that</hi> chap. 50. verſ. 17. <hi>As if they had not given teſtimonies enough before of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, after</hi> 17 <hi>years, you find them renewing it, praying him to</hi> forgive them their treſpaſſes againſt him. <hi>But more than</hi> 20 <hi>years are paſt, ſince our King's Act of Oblivion, without any penitent Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations hitherto; inſtead thereof, we have heard of repeated Conſpiracies, and of late intended Inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Maſſacres of the King's Loyal Subjects, of Blunderbuſſes to take away his Life, with his Royal Brothers, by whoſe ſole Grace they hold their own.</hi> And now, Beloved, one would think, that theſe Examples of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and our preſent Sovereign, might prevail with any, to lay aſide Anger, and to pardon their Enemies; few ever receiving ſuch wrongs; and I wiſh to God I could not ſay, few ever ſo pardoning. But if this be not of force enough, let me intreat thoſe haughty ſpirits to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate upon the Lord of Glory, deſcending from Heaven, and becoming a ſervant for our ſakes; and after 33, or 34 years converſe upon Earth, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf to the ſhamefull and painfull death of the Croſs, whereon he received all the affronts, and ſharp uſage, wherewith malicious cruelty could
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49251:11"/>torment him: His nailed hands, and bored feet, diſtilled and dropped bloud; nay his whole body in every particular part endured a ſeveral Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion: Yet then, even then, it was; he ſhewed himſelf the higheſt example of (what he taught his Diſciples, and in them us) loving our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, crying with a loud and ſtrong cry, not for himſelf, but for thoſe who ſo inhumanely butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered him; <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they doe.</hi> I might now, from Examples, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſs this duty, as from other things, ſo from your intereſt, from the eternal intereſt of your bodies and ſouls; <hi>For as you forgive men their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, ſo will your heavenly Father forgive you yours.</hi> But I have been, I fear, too long upon this point, I muſt haſten to another.</p>
               <p>Therefore, ſecondly, from <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s entertaining his brethren, who came into <hi>Egypt</hi> to buy Corn for themſelves, and their little ones, by reaſon of the great famine that then raged in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and other parts adjacent to <hi>Egypt.</hi> Let me propoſe another duty incumbent upon us, eſpecially at ſuch ſolemn meetings, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Poor. And this is ſo inſeparable from a true Chriſtian feaſt, that I never read of the one, without the other. I might preſs this duty, had I time, from ſeveral arguments, but I ſhall confine my ſelf to what may naturally be inferred from the Text, concluding this particular by way of Direction, upon whom chiefly you are to diſpoſe your Charity. <hi>Egypt,</hi> by an eaſie Allegory, may be taken for the World; by the <hi>eleven brethren,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49251:12"/>you may underſtand the poor and neceſſitous; and by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> are repreſented thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with riches, to the end they may ſupply out of their ſtore to them, who labour under need and poverty. <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſo well managed his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and ſo effectually provided againſt that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging famine that then was in the land, that I read in ſeveral Hiſtories; That the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſuppoſed him to be more than man; and therefore in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages adored him as a God, under the name of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapis:</hi> I am ſure all ye, who abound in Riches, have the ſame honourable employment entruſted to you, though your Province is not ſo large; but then you have your Commiſſion from a greater King than <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> viz. <hi>the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> And if the poor ſhould want relief, when you can aſſiſt them, you will have this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon you, that whereas <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſupplied the wants of a great Kingdom with the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, in an extreme want of ſeven years; you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a few indigent people to ſtarve in a great plenty of all things. But I hope better things of you, eſpecially having been an eye-witneſs; how free and liberal you have been at our laſt Annual meetings. And here, if I may guide your hands, in your more liberal diſtributions, <hi>I would propoſe thoſe Loyal perſons as larger Objects of your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who either ſuffered in the ſervice of the late Royal Martyr; or, of late, in their faithfull adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our preſent Sovereign; when the Tragedy of Forty-one was, if poſſible, in more diſmal circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, deſigned to be re-acted, by ſome of the ſame men, but all of the ſame Principles with the former.</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49251:12"/>And I am ſure my Text will juſtifie my advice, wherein though <hi>Joſeph</hi> entertained all his brethren at a feaſt, <hi>yet</hi> Benjamin<hi>'s Meſs was five times ſo much as any of theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, Did <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a pious, chaſt, and religious Man, yet entertain his brethren after that manner, as you have heard? and was his Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice followed by the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, by our bleſſed Saviour and the Primitive Chriſtians? Why then, let us not regard the unjuſt cenſures of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable men, as to our preſent Aſſembly. Thoſe Writers did but dream, who fanſied the fruit of the forbidden tree, to be that of the Vine: No, no, God never made the Vine onely to tempt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and that he ſhould not taſte thereof. The Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet</hi> indeed denied it to his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers; but God himſelf was pleaſed to accept of it in Sacrifices, and the bleſſed Jeſus put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the expence of a Miracle, that men might know his ſenſe thereof. But here let me beg of you, not to miſconſtrue what I have ſaid; and do not think, that whilſt I plead for the innocent mirth of Chriſtians, that you may behave your ſelves, as if you were at the <hi>Roman</hi> Bacchanals, or, which is very like, their Carnivals now.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>I ſhall ſum up all in a word or two, by way of Exhortation. Do not, O do not abuſe God's good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that which he hath indulged to us, to cheer and refreſh us; Let us not make uſe of it to the diſhonouring his Image in us, to the unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelves, and putting on the ſhapes of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49251:13"/>beaſts, as too too many doe. I ſhall give you but one direction herein; be ſure none of you touch that glaſs, whereby you may be rendred leſs fitting for God's ſervice. As for drunkenneſs and debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, let it not be ſo much as mentioned, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh ſuch Chriſtian Meetings; When you are at Dinner, remember, that as the <hi>Jews</hi> after their Sacrifices, ſo you juſt before were worſhipping God at his holy Temple; Let your carriage at the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing entertainment baffle the idle clamours of thoſe who oppoſe ſuch Meetings of Love; Shew to them, that you can be ſober, as well as cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; and that you can be men, without laying aſide the Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Let this meeting be like that of the Primitive Chriſtians, of whom <hi>Pliny</hi> wrote to the Emperour <hi>Trajan,</hi> an engagement to Vertue, and an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from ſin and iniquity. Be conſtant in your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to our Engliſh <hi>Joſeph;</hi> Continue true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Our eſtabliſh'd Church, which, beſt of all others, teaches how to <hi>render to God, the things which are God's; and to Caeſar, the things which are Caeſar's.</hi> Let us follow St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s advice, and <hi>doe good to all men, eſpecially to thoſe of the houſhold of faith;</hi> Nay, let our charity be more extenſive, and let us imbrace even the Diſſenters themſelves, though not by proſtituting the Churches Orders to their peeviſhneſs and wantonneſs, but by praying for them, that they may return to their duty to our common Mother, the eſtabliſh't Church of <hi>England,</hi> that ſo at length we may all be loving brethren, and with one unanimous conſent, may with one heart, and one voice glorifie God, the Father of us
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49251:13"/>all. If any of you have had that grand happineſs of Mankind, a true friend, doe your utmoſt to preſerve him ſo: Nay, if any of you hath an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who hath done you wrong or injury, imitate <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and our preſent Sovereign; but above all, our bleſſed Saviour, ſingle out that perſon, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him: If any Object of Charity comes into your thoughts, eſpecially of poor loyal perſons, take hold of the occaſion, accordingly as God hath enabled you. Theſe and the like things, if you perform, you need not fear, but that this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Banquet will be an Antepaſt of an eternal Feaſt in the Heavens; Which God grant. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
